{"tossups": [{"question": "As a result of this campaign, the first instance of an American Thanksgiving holiday was celebrated. The losing side in this campaign was hoping to meet up with Barry St. Leger [[leh-JEHR]] in an attempt to split the colonies. France allied with America after this campaign, which had skirmishes at Bemis [[BEE-miss]] Heights and Freeman's Farm. For the point, name this 1777 military campaign in which the Continental Army defeated John Burgoyne's forces in upstate New York.", "answer": "<b><u>Saratoga</u></b> Campaign (accept Battles of <b><u>Saratoga</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This location\u2019s current structure was designed by two Greek geometers, Isidore of Miletus [[my-LEE-tuss]] and Anthemius [[an-THEE-mee-us]] of Tralles [[TRAH-less]]. Following the Nika Revolt, Justinian I ordered this location to be rebuilt a third time to become, at the time, the largest church in Eastern Orthodoxy. Built in the imperial capital of the Byzantine Empire, for the point, what is this place of worship which was converted into a mosque following the fall of Constantinople?", "answer": "<b><u>Hagia Sophia</u></b> [[\"EYE\"-ah soh-FEE-ah]] (or Holy <b><u>Hagia Sophia</u></b> Grand Mosque; accept Church of <b><u>Hagia Sophia</u></b>; accept phonetically correct pronunciation)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The oligarchic \"Family Compact\" dominated the politics of this province until the anti-British Rebellions of 1837. Due to illegally shelving a cap-and-trade program in this province, the government of Doug Ford was forced to accept a mandated carbon tax. That man's brother, Rob Ford, was the mayor of a city in this province, facing a 2013 substance abuse scandal before being hospitalized. The 1813 Battle of York saw the raiding of the city of Toronto in, for the point, what most populous province of Canada?", "answer": "<b><u>Ontario</u></b> (accept <b><u>Upper Canada</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "First borrowed from the Western Wei, this dynasty used the <em>fubing</em> system of militia recruitment to pacify countryside revolts. This dynasty introduced the <em>Jiedushi</em> [[GEE-DOO-SHE]], a commander-turned-military governor, whose ranks included the rebellious An Lushan. This dynasty's future emperors Taizong and his father Gaozu [[GOW-ZOO]] overthrew the short-lived Sui [[SWEH]] Dynasty. For the point, name this medieval dynasty that included the only female independent ruler of China, Empress Wu.", "answer": "<b><u>Tang</u></b> Dynasty (or <b><u>T\u00e1ng</u></b>ch\u00e1o; accept D\u00e0 <b><u>T\u00e1ng</u></b>; or Great <b><u>Tang</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Alongside astrology, this field was covered in the most popular work attributed to the legendary figure Hermes Trismegistus [[TRIS-meh-GIS-tus]]. Common aims of this practice included the development of panaceas to cure all diseases as well as chrysopoeia [[kry-soh-PEE-uh]], or the transformation of base metals into gold. The Philosopher's Stone was a goal of, for the point, what proto-scientific field which was practiced in the medieval Western and Islamic worlds?", "answer": "<b><u>Alchemy</u></b> (or <b><u>Alchemist</u></b>s; accept <b><u>Al-k\u012bmiy\u0101</u></b>; accept <b><u>Khumeia</u></b>; prompt on general terms like \"medicine\" or \"magic\" until \"Chrysopoeia\")", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "On this island, the Kempeitai [[kem-PAY-tie]] orchestrated the Sandakan Death Marches of Australian and British POWs. On this island, the occupying Japanese publicly executed Syarif Muhammad Alkadrie [[al-KAH-dree]] and the royal family to discredit the Pontianak [[PON-tee-ah-nahk]] Sultanate. During the Konfrontasi [[kon-fron-TAH-see]], the majority of fighting occurred on this island, which is known as Kalimantan to the Indonesians. Brunei and a part of Malaysia are on, for the point, what Southeast Asian island, the third largest on Earth?", "answer": "<b><u>Borneo</u></b> (accept <b><u>Kalimantan</u></b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Many of the scientists involved with making these objects were relocated after World War Two to the Redstone Arsenal in Alabama. One of these objects crossed the K\u00e1rm\u00e1n line to become the first man-made object to enter space. These weapons were developed at Peenem\u00fcnde [[PEH-nuh-MYOON-duh]] by a team led by Werner von Braun [[VER-nuh fahn BRAWN]]. For the point, name these rocket weapons developed by the Nazi military to terrorize Allied civilians.", "answer": "<b><u>V-2</u></b> Rockets (or <b><u>Vergeltungswaffe Zwei</u></b>; accept <b><u>Aggregat-4</u></b>; or <b><u>A4</u></b>; prompt on \"V Weapon\" or \"V Rocket\"; prompt on \"Rocket(s)\")", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "The Flexner Report contributed to the closure of approximately 30 percent of these institutions in the 1910s. Reverend Dickson supported another figure in attending one of these institutions, where she concurrently worked at Blockley Almshouse. The requirement of a degree before entrance into these institutions was instituted in 1876 as part of the reforms made by Johns Hopkins, which also promoted clinical learning. For the point, name these institutions whose students often perform dissections.", "answer": "<b><u>Medical school</u></b>s (prompt on \"schools\" or \"universities\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Over two thousand years prior to the British disaster, this man led a successful military campaign against barbarians located on the Gallipoli [[gah-LEE-poh-lee]] Peninsula. This man's father had been ostracized, but this man was able to get Thucydides [[thoo-SIH-do-deez]] ostracized thanks to his own political connections. Like his sons and sister, this man died from a plague that was rampaging in his city during the Peloponnesian War. For the point, name this statesman and orator during the Golden Age of Athens.", "answer": "<b><u>Pericles</u></b> [[peh-RIH-kleez]]", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This leader gave a speech in the U.S. Senate stating that the phrase \u201call men are created equal\u201d did not apply to African-Americans while attempting to position himself as a \"compromise candidate\" for the Democratic Party in 1860. This man avoided an assassination attempt when George Atzerodt [[AT-zeh-rot]] got drunk instead. Simultaneous to that event, this man's predecessor was assassinated at Ford's Theatre. For the point, name this U.S. president who assumed office after the death of Abraham Lincoln.", "answer": "<b><u>A</u></b>ndrew <b><u>Johnson</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In this nation, former Spartakiad [[spar-tah-KEE-ahd]] trainer Klement Gottwald [[GOHT-vahlt]] overthrew the democratically elected Edvard Bene\u0161 [[BEH-nesh]] in a 1948 coup. To curb Hungarian expansion, this nation formed the Little Entente [[ahn-TAHNT]] with Romania and Yugoslavia. Following the Munich Conference, this nation was forced to cede the Sudetenland [[soo-DEH-ten-land]] to Nazi Germany. Leonid Brezhnev [[BREZH-nef]] sent in the Soviet military to crush, for the point, what nation during the Prague Spring?", "answer": "<b><u>Czechoslovak</u></b>ia (accept <b><u>Czechoslovak</u></b> Socialist Republic; do not accept \"Czechia,\" \"Czech Republic,\" or \"Slovakia\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Philosopher James Otteson wrote [this man's] <em>Marketplace of Life</em>, explaining the cohesion between two 18th century works by this thinker. Chancellor of the Exchequer [[ex-CHEH-ker]] Charles Townsend employed this man to tutor his son following this professor's popular Glasgow lectures. A description of the \"invisible hand\" was first described in this man's <em>Theory of Moral Sentiments</em> and later used by economists to promote <em>Laissez-Faire</em> [[leh-seh-FEHR]] policies. For the point, name this economist who wrote <em>The</em> <em>Wealth of Nations</em>.", "answer": "Adam <b><u>Smith</u></b>", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Economics"}, {"question": "In this document, a provision was included to allow Canada to join the United States at any time. The first president under this document was Samuel Huntington, and a majority of nine states was needed to pass any legislation under it. The two main authors of this document were Benjamin Franklin and Silas Deane, and it was replaced less than ten years after its ratification. For the point, name this original framing document that was replaced by the U.S. Constitution.", "answer": "<b><u>Articles of Confederation</u></b> and Perpetual Union", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man constructed a new capital named for himself on top of the old city of Avaris. The Temple of Beit el-Wali was devoted to this ruler after his forces re-asserted control of Nubia. This ruler's charioteers battled Muwatalli II and the Hittites at one ancient battle. This ruler conquered Canaan and Syria, despite being forced to sue for peace after Kadesh [[KAY-desh]]. For the point, name this \"great\" Egyptian pharaoh, son of Seti [[SEH-tee]].", "answer": "<b><u>Ramses II</u></b> (or <b><u>Ramses the Great</u></b>; accept <b><u>Ramesses</u></b> in place of \"Ramses\"; accept <b><u>Ozymandias</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "One of these edicts was used to seize private steel production facilities to support the Korean war effort, but that attempt was deemed unconstitutional. The official \"first\" of these statutes was retroactively assigned to a Lincoln-era memorandum justifying detaining political prisoners. Franklin Delano Roosevelt set a new standard by issuing over 3700 of these directives. For the point, name this type of directive issued directly by the president of the United States.", "answer": "<b><u>Executive Order</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Named after a 2010s action film, the concept of \"Wolf Warrior Diplomacy\" has been applied to this man's aggressive foreign policy. Austerity measures and an aim for greater transparency was the purpose of this leader's \"Eight Point Regulation,\" a reform of his Politburo [[POH-lit-boo-roh]]. This man succeed Hu Jintao [[HOO-JIN-TAO]] following his voluntary retirement in 2012. The writer of <em>The Governance of China</em> is, for the point, which General Secretary of the Chinese Communist Party?", "answer": "<b><u>Xi</u></b> [[SHEE]] Jinping (prompt on \"Jinping\")", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "With Offa of Mercia [[MEHR-see-ah]], this man abandoned the Roman <em>sou</em> gold coin for a silver-based currency and established the <em>livre</em> as a standard. The use of lowercase letters in Western Europe became standardized by Alcuin [[AL-kwin]] of York while in this man\u2019s court. This son of Pepin the Short was declared Holy Roman Emperor in an 800 C.E. coronation by Pope Leo III. For the point, name this \"Great\" Carolingian king of the Franks.", "answer": "<b><u>Charlemagne</u></b> (accept <b><u>Charles the Great</u></b>; accept <b><u>Carolus Magnus</u></b>; accept <b><u>Charles I</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This city was the site of the first recorded workers\u2019 strike in history when Polish artisans refused to work if they couldn\u2019t vote. 350 years after this city\u2019s founding, visitors could see full-sized replicas of three ships, the <em>Susan Constant</em>, <em>Godspeed</em>, and <em>Discovery</em>. Those three ships, under the leadership of Christopher Newport, brought the first colonists to this city. For the point, name this city, the first permanent English settlement in the Americas.", "answer": "<b><u>Jamestown</u></b>, Virginia", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man eloped with his wife in 1795 after being rejected by that woman's father, Judge John Cleves Symmes. Prior to Ronald Reagan, this man held the distinction of being the oldest man elected U.S. president. As a result of this man's success during the War of 1812, his slogan in the Election of 1840 was \"Tippecanoe and Tyler too.\" For the point, name this president who died of pneumonia, serving the shortest presidential term in history in 1841.", "answer": "<b><u>W</u></b>illiam Henry <b><u>Harrison</u></b> (prompt on Harrison; do not accept or prompt on \"Benjamin Harrison\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Following the Srebrenica [[sreh-breh-NEET-sah]] genocide, this group conducted a two-week bombing campaign, Operation Deliberate Force, and deployed a UN-mandated peacekeeping force called IFOR [[EYE-FOR]]. This group invoked Article 5 of its charter after the September 11th attacks and conducted eight operations, including Operation Eagle Assist and Operation Active Endeavor. Formed after a namesake treaty was signed on April 4, 1949, for the point, what is this intergovernmental alliance of thirty countries headquartered near Mons, Belgium?", "answer": "<b><u>North Atlantic Treaty Organization</u></b> (or <b><u>NATO</u></b>; or <b><u>Organisation du trait\u00e9 de</u></b> <b><u>l'Atlantique nord</u></b>; or <b><u>OTAN</u></b>; prompt on \"North Atlantic Alliance\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man was inspired by the work of Francois Marius Granet [grah-NEH] to create the painting <em>The House of Representatives</em> in 1821. This Nativist quoted the Book of Numbers by saying, \u201cWhat hath God wrought?\u201d while telecommunicating to Baltimore from Washington, D.C. This man\u2019s namesake code represents the Latin alphabet through dots and dashes. For the point, name this American inventor of the single-wire telegraph.", "answer": "Samuel <b><u>Morse</u></b> (or Samuel Finley Breese <b><u>Morse</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This country was the site of the MacDonald House bombing. This country\u2019s first leader was advised by the Dutch economist Albert Winsemius [[win-SEH-mee-us]], and this country's 1964 race riots are remembered on Racial Harmony Day. This country's People\u2019s Action Party implemented the death penalty for drug offenses and outlawed chewing gum. For the point, name this country which was led by Lee Kuan Yew, a city-state at the tip of the Malay Peninsula.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Singapore</u></b> (accept Republik <b><u>Singapura</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "When this vessel was completed in 1907, it was briefly the largest ship in the world, though that title was taken three months later by the R.M.S. <em>Mauretania</em>, this vessel's sister ship. This ship\u2019s career ended abruptly off the coast of Ireland when <em>U-20</em> sent a single torpedo into the ship\u2019s starboard side. For the point, name this ocean liner that a German U-Boat torpedoed and sunk in May 1915, contributing to the United States' entry into World War One.", "answer": "RMS <em><b><u>Lusitania</u></b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A conference codenamed Sextant in this city included the Allied offer to Chiang Kai-Shek of full control of French Indochina at war's end, which he declined. The Abdeen Palace incident of 1942 in this city led to the forced resignation of King Farouk I. This city's Tahrir Square was the site of anti-Mubarak demonstrations during the larger \"Arab Spring\" movement. For the point, name this metropolis along the Nile Delta, the capital of Egypt.", "answer": "<b><u>Cairo</u></b> (accept <b><u>Cairo</u></b> Conference)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This ruler had his half-brother, Odo, arrested for unknown reasons and built the Battle Abbey to honor the fallen of a historically significant victory. This ruler crushed the rebellion of Edward the Exile during the Harrying of the North. This king came to power by winning a three-sided succession war against the Norwegian Harald Hardrada [[har-DRAH-dah]] and the Anglo-Saxon Harold Godwinson, a conflict which culminated in the Battle of Hastings. For the point, name this first Norman king of England.", "answer": "<b><u>William the Conqueror</u></b> (or <b><u>William I</u></b>; accept <b><u>William the Bastard</u></b>; prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Secretary of State John Hay characterized this relatively brief conflict as a \u201csplendid little war.\u201d One of the final actions of this conflict was a lopsided U.S. victory in the Battle of Manila Bay, which book-ended the origin of this conflict on the other side of the globe, an explosion in Havana\u2019s harbor that destroyed the U.S.S. <em>Maine</em>. For the point, name this war, during which Theodore Roosevelt and his \u201cRough Riders\u201d charged up San Juan Hill.", "answer": "<b><u>Spanish-American</u></b> War", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The historical court scholar Kanke [[KAHN-keh]], who was exiled to this country's Chikuzen [[chih-KOO-zen]] Province in the 9th century, is worshipped in this nation as the primary deity of scholarship known as Tenjin. In this nation's myth, the three-eyed crow known as <em>yata-garasu</em> [[YAH-tah-geh-RAH-soo]] led its mythological Emperor Jimmu to Yamato. Historical figures such as Odu Nobunaga and Emperor Meiji have been worshipped as <em>kami</em> [[KAH-mee]] in, for the point, which East Asian nation?", "answer": "<b><u>Japan</u></b> (or <b><u>Nippon</u></b>-koku; or <b><u>Nihon</u></b>-koku)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Dr. Pepper, breast implants, and 3-D printing were all invented in this state. Until World War One, this state recognized its own dialect of German as an official language. One city in the northern part of this state is known as the \"Helium Capital of the World.\" A chain of amusement parks originated in this state and took its name from six different countries controlling it throughout history. Six Flags originated in, for the point, what Lonestar State?", "answer": "<b><u>Texas</u></b> (accept <b><u>Texas</u></b> German; accept Six Flags Over <b><u>Texas</u></b>)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "This man's legacy includes lending his name to a spacecraft launched to map the surface of Venus as well as to two dwarf galaxies. After upsetting royals in his native country, this explorer was sent to serve in Morocco. Before being able to finish his final voyage, this explorer was killed in the modern-day Philippines in 1521. For the point, name this Portuguese explorer whose Spanish fleet was the first to circumnavigate the globe.", "answer": "Ferdinand <b><u>Magellan</u></b> (or Fern\u00e3o de <b><u>Magalh\u00e3es</u></b>; or Fernando de <b><u>Magallanes</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This nation suffered a widespread blindness epidemic in the 1990s caused by <em>gualfarina</em> [[gwahl-fah-REE-nah]] moonshine. This nation experienced economic destitution in the 1990s due to a lack of foreign aid from the recently fallen USSR. This nation sent convicts and political undesirables to the U.S. during the Mariel [[mah-ree-EL]] Boatlift. The Obama administration facilitated a namesake \"thaw\" in the 2010s which normalized relations with this nation. For the point, name this Caribbean nation ruled by the Castro regime for six decades.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Cuba</u></b> (or Rep\u00fablica de <b><u>Cuba</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<em>Bitter Fruit</em>, a novel written in this nation, details the racial tensions that this country experienced in the 1980s and 90s. <em>Cry the Beloved Country</em> was written by an author from this nation, who was born in the colony of Natal [[nah-TAHL]]. Some of this nation's literature is written in Afrikaans, and <em>Long Walk to Freedom</em> was about the fight to end institutionalized segregation in this country. For the point, name this country which is home to authors including Alan Paton [[PAT-un]] and Nelson Mandela.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>South Africa</u></b> (or <b><u>RSA</u></b>)", "metadata": "Literature - World Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "Used exclusively during this ritual, the <em>Mahmal</em> [[mahk-MAHL]] is a camel carriage kept empty for ceremonial purposes. Advice on how to undertake this ritual was given by Mughal court official Safi ibn Vali, who wrote about his arrival to the port of Mocha. The Ayyubid sultan Saladin ended the taxation imposed for performing this task by local Hejazi [[heh-JAH-zee]] magistrates. Mansa Musa devalued gold in Egypt while undertaking, for the point, what mandatory journey in which a Muslim travels to Mecca?", "answer": "<b><u>Hajj</u></b> (accept <b><u>Hadji</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A poem by this author was criticized in the anti-imperialist satirical essay \"To the Person Sitting in Darkness\" by Mark Twain. The \"Great Game\" between British Empire and Russia sets the backdrop for this author's novel <em>Kim</em>. The annexation of the Philippines is encouraged by this British author in his essay \"The White Man's Burden.\" For the point, name this interventionist British author of <em>The Jungle Book</em>.", "answer": "Rudyard <b><u>Kipling</u></b> (or Joseph Rudyard <b><u>Kipling</u></b>)", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "Following this war, Krzysztof Penderecki [[kuh-SHEE-shtoff pen-deh-RETS-kyee]] wrote a piece to commemorate the destruction of one city during it. Aaron Copland's \"Fanfare for the Common Man\" was written to symbolize one nation's entry into this war. During this war, Dmitri Shostakovich [[shoh-stah-KOH-vitch]] wrote his \"Leningrad\" Symphony in response to a German invasion. For the point, name this 20th-century war during which the short-short-short-long motif of Beethoven's 5th Symphony was used to celebrate \"V-E\" Day.", "answer": "<b><u>World</u></b> War <b><u>Two</u></b> (accept <b><u>WW Two</u></b>; accept <b><u>Second World</u></b> War)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "In this city, George Turner Marsh imported koi fish for a garden at the 1894 World\u2019s Fair. The overturning of measures to segregate schools in this city paved the way for the Gentlemen\u2019s Agreement, which reduced immigration from a Pacific nation. Many of those immigrants passed through Angel Island en route to this city, which experienced an influx of Japanese migrants after a catastrophic 1906 earthquake. For the point, name this northern California city on a namesake bay.", "answer": "<b><u>San Francisco</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This location\u2019s construction was initially proposed by James Madison in 1783, but it was not built until John Adams appropriated $5,000 for it. Since then, this location has been expanded numerous times by Ainsworth Rand Spofford, and under the leadership of Herbert Putnam this institution became the first in the United States to house over one million books. For the point, name this oldest federal cultural institution in the United States.", "answer": "<b><u>Library of Congress</u></b> (prompt on \"LC\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}], "bonuses": []}